Guide to the Shau Wing Chan Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Shau Wing Chan papers
1911-1994
SC0421
Chan, Shau Wing, 1907-1986.
2.75 Linear feet (7 boxes)
Notebooks, exams, reading notes, and a draft of his thesis from his graduate studies, 1930-1933; professional and personal correspondence, 1938-1949, including letters pertaining to his immigration status; correspondence, memoranda, and reports pertaining to Stanford administrative and departmental matters, 1935-1982; and family papers, 1911-1994. Included in the family papers are extensive correspondence between Chan and his wife Anna during his trips away from home, 1938-1960; letters (many in Chinese) from his brothers Shou Yi Ch'en, 1937-1977, Stanley Hong (Shou Hong) Chan, 1938-1975, and Shau Wa (Wally) Chan, 1941-1950; correspondence of Chan's son Loren B. Chan with his parents and uncles, 1964-1989; personal documents of Anna Mae Chan, 1911-1994; Shau Wing Chan's passports and travel papers, 1937-1982; and some ephemera from China, 1925-1926.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Loren B. Chan, 1987, 1988, and 1995.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Chan received his M.A. (1932) and his Ph.D. (1937) in English from Stanford University. He joined the Stanford faculty in 1938 and retired in 1972. He was instrumental in founding what is now the Department of Asian Languages, serving as its executive head from 1958-1962.
Description of the Collection
Notebooks, exams, reading notes, and a draft of his thesis from his graduate studies, 1930-1933; professional and personal correspondence, 1938-1949, including letters pertaining to his immigration status; correspondence, memoranda, and reports pertaining to Stanford administrative and departmental matters, 1935-1982; and family papers, 1911-1994. Included in the family papers are extensive correspondence between Chan and his wife Anna during his trips away from home, 1938-1960; letters (many in Chinese) from his brothers Shou Yi Ch'en, 1937-1977, Stanley Hong (Shou Hong) Chan, 1938-1975, and Shau Wa (Wally) Chan, 1941-1950; correspondence of Chan's son Loren B. Chan with his parents and uncles, 1964-1989; personal documents of Anna Mae Chan, 1911-1994; Shau Wing Chan's passports and travel papers, 1937-1982; and some ephemera from China, 1925-1926.
Access Terms
Ch'en, Shou-yi, 1899-; Chan, Anna Mae.; Chan, Loren Briggs, 1943-; Chan, Shau Hong.; Chan, Shau Wa.; Chan, Shau Wing, 1907-1986.; Stanford University. Department of Asian Languages. Faculty.; Stanford University. Department of English.; Chinese Americans--California.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Life History (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Student Life (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - English 211 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - English 203, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - English 181, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - English 168 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - English 158, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - French A111, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - English 216, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Romance Languages A201, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Romance Languages A161, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - English 235, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - English 225, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - English 192 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - English 217b (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Examination booklets, 1933 and undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Thesis, draft of (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Thesis notes (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reading notes (vol. 17) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reading notes (vol. 18) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, outgoing, 1940-1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, outgoing: letters of recommendation (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, incoming: A-F (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, incoming: G-O (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, incoming: P-Z and unidentified (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence concerning Chan’s immigration status 1938-1940 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Book reviews, typescript (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Stanford University, administrative correspondence and notices, 1940-1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Stanford University memoranda, reports, etc., 1935-1949 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stanford University, School of Humanities, organization of (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Seminars on morale and peace (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Stanford Alumni Association papers, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - United Nations Awards (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Reprints (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Slides: ca.1948: Hong Kong (Box 4)
  - Slides: ca.1948: Macau (Box 4)
  - Slides: ca.1948: Ladies Style (Box 4)
  - Slides: ca.1948: People (Box 4)
  - Slides: ca.1948: Border (Box 4)
  - Slides: ca.1948: Hong Kong and Kowloon by Night (Box 4)
  - Slides: ca.1948: Kowloon (Box 4)
  - Slides: ca.1948: Tiger Balm Garden (Box 4)
  - Slides: ca.1948: (untitled) (Box 4)
  - OS box storage: Photograph of Chan in dinner party honoring Superior Judge Thomas A. Foley Feb. 28, 1939 (Box OS)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1995-257
  - Shau Wing Chan: eulogy, memorial resolution, death certificate, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Immigration papers, letters, and passports (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Calligraphy in the hand of Shau Wing Chan's father (Chi-tong Chan, 1863-1918) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera from China: Sun Yat-sen postcard, 1925; grade book of John C. Griggs, teacher at Lingnam University, Canton, 1925-26; and booklet on a missionary school in Ningpo, Chekian province (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Amma Mae Chan: eulogies, birth and death certificates, passport, and school grade cards (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Applications and resumes (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Copyrights (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - book reviews, 1937-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ray Lyman Wilbur, letters to Chan re Stanford matters, 1933-1943; and notice of Wilbur's death, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stanford, 1930-1936: expense record, student body cards, two letters (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stanford, 1938-1982: administrative correspondence and ID card; also includes letters from other colleges and travel papers (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hip Wo School: two lettes re appointment, 1939 and 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National Shantung (Shandong) University, letters, 1937 (some in Chinese) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Utah State University, 1941, 1964: correspondence with King Hendricks and others re Chan's lectures there (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Loren B. chan to his parents, 1966-1972, re his graduate work at UCLA and subsequent teaching jobs (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Loren B. Chan with his parents, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Anna and Wing Chan, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Chan family, summer 1951 (Chan was teaching summer school at Pomona College) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Anna and Wing Chan, 1948, during Chan's trip to China (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: family letters to Chan while he was in China, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Anna and Wing Chan, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Anna and Wing chan, 1944 (Chan was teqaching summer school at the University of Utah) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Anna and Wing Chan, 1936-1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Helen Lei Ch'en (wife of Shou Yi Ch'en) to Anna Chan, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: unsent Chinese letter by Wing Chan, ca. 1930-1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: letters from Annie Tak-yi Chan Ng (Wing's eldest siste), in chinese, 1938-1940; unsent letter in Chinese by Wing, ca. 1941; letters from Annie's children Poon Keung Ng, 1955, and Ng To Yeuk, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Shou Yi Ch'en to Wing Chan, in Chinese, 1937-1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Shou Yi Ch'en to Wing and Anna Chan, in English, 1940-1977; obituaries for Shou Yi Ch'en, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Stanley (Shau Hong) Chan to Wing Chan, mostly in Chinese, 1938-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Lily Luella Lum Chan (wife of Stanley) to Anna and Wing chan, 1936-1940, in English (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Shau Wa (Wally) Chan to Anna and Wing Chan, 1941-1950, in Chinese and English; leter from Maude Martha Don Chan, wife of Shau Wa, 1955; and eulogy for Shau Wa Chan, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Shou Yi Ch'en to Loren B. Chan, 1966-1975, mostly in Chinese (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Shau Wing and Anna Chan to and from Loren B. Chan, 1967-1989, in English (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Shau Wing Chan's Chinese signet seal ("chop"); and his rubber signature stamp used while chairperson of the Dept. of Asian Languages (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2014.028; 0.25 Linear feet (1 volume)
  - Diary, 1938 (Box 1)
General note
See AM 95-032 for Stanford student memorabilia owned by Chan.